<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

    <properties>

        <title>AspectWerkz</title>

        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>

    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Features">

            <subsection name="AspectWerkz supports the following features">

                <p>

                    This is a very incomplete list, see the documentation for all features.

                </p>

                <ul>

                    <li>

                        Very high-performant. Weaved code is entirely statically compiled.

                        AspectWerkz ranks 1st or 2nd in most of the benchmarks. Read more about the figures

                        on the <a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/AW/AspectWerkz+performance">AspectWerkz Bench project pages</a>.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                         <b>Annotation support</b>: Matching on annotations (both JavaDoc and JSR-175). Supports user-defined annotations,

                         retrieval of annotations. Both JavaDoc and JSR-175 annotations are accessed through one

                         single API and both schemes are strongly typed.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Aspects, advices and introductions are written in <b>plain old

                        Java code</b>. I.e. no new language to learn, no new compilation

                        phases, no need to tell your manager ;-). Will work seamlessly in

                        any IDE, debugger, refactoring tool and test framework.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        The target classes can be regular POJOs (Plain Old Java

                        Objects), i.e. do not require to have an interface.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Weaving</b> (bytecode modification) at compile time, load time and runtime.

                        Hooks in and transforms classes loaded by

                        <b>any</b> class loader

                        except the bootstrap class loader. Which basically means that

                        you can easily transform any (legacy) application or external

                        library apart from rt.jar both at runtime and compile time.

                        <br/>

                        <code>JSR-163 JVMTI</code> is supported for Java 1.5 usage as well.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>The join point model</b> supports: staticinitialization, method execution and call, constructor execution and call,

                        field access, field modification, catch handlers, cflow, within and withincode, hasmethod and hasfield. All advice works with all join points.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Rich semantics</b> allow to access runtime information about the join point within the advice using regular types without any

                        casting or object array access. Reflective access to runtime information is also possible.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Introductions/Inter type declarations (also called Mixins)</b>, i.e. the possibility

                        to add interfaces and implementations to existing classes.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>META-INF/aop.xml container</b>: Support for deploying several

                        <code>aop.xml</code> Aspect defintion/deployment files alongside deployed

                        application (

                        <code>WEB-INF/aop.xml</code>,

                        <code>META-INF/aop.xml</code>) and have them following

                        the classloader hierarchy.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Annotation definition</b>. Define your aspects and mixins using annotations using wether standardized Java 5 Annotations

                        (JSR-175) or Java 1.3/1.4 custom doclet with strongly typed access.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                         <b>XML definition</b>. Define your aspects and mixins using XML. The XML definition can also be used to refine,

                         override and resolve the annotation definition.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Pluggable aspect manager</b> that can make it work seamlessly with IoC frameworks like Spring

                        or PicoContainer.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Support several different <b>deployment models</b> (scope) for aspects (perJVM(singleton), perClass, perInstance)

                        and for mixin (perInstance, perClass, perJVM(singleton)).

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Hot deployment</b>, aspects can be deployed and undeployed at runtime using a simple API.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Fine-grained pattern language for selecting the join points.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Highly orthogonal underlying model. All advice works with all join points and pointcut composition

                        supports mixing all kinds of pointcuts.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        "Offline" transformation (can be used as a post-processor).

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Support for passing configuration parameters to the advices through

                        the definition.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        Simple usage and configuration.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                    <li>

                        <b>Extensible container architecture</b> allows to run any Aspects (AspectWerkz, Spring AOP, AOP Alliance, subset of AspectJ)

                        within the AspectWerkz runtime.

                    </li>

                    <br/>

                </ul>

            </subsection>

        </section>

    </body>

</document>



