<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Overview</title>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="AspectWerkz 2">
            <subsection name="Simple, high-performant, dynamic, lightweight and powerful AOP for Java">
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> is a dynamic, lightweight and
                    high-performant AOP framework for Java.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> offers both power and simplicity
                    and will help you to easily integrate AOP in both new and
                    existing projects.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> utilizes bytecode
                    modification to weave your classes at project build-time, class load time or runtime. It hooks in
                    using standardized JVM level APIs.

                    It has a rich and highly orthogonal join point model. Aspects, advices and
                    introductions are written in plain Java and your target
                    classes can be regular POJOs.

                    You have the possibility to add, remove and re-structure
                    advice as well as swapping the implementation of your
                    introductions at runtime.
                                            
                    Your aspects can be defined using either Java 5 annotations,
                    Java 1.3/1.4 custom doclets or a simple XML definition
                    file.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> provides an API to use the very same aspects for <i>proxies</i>, hence
                    providing a transparent experience, allowing a smooth transition
                    for users familiar with proxies.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> performance is reported in this <a href="http://docs.codehaus.org/display/AW/AOP+Benchmark">separate project</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> is Free Software. The
                    <a href="license.html">LGPL-style</a> license allows the use of
                    <code>AspectWerkz 2.0</code>
                    in both commercial and open source projects.
                    <br/>
                </p>
                <p>
                    Sponsored by
                    <a href="http://www.bea.com">BEA Systems</a>
                    <img src="bea.bmp" alt="BEA Systems"/>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="AspectJ and AspectWerkz join forces">
                <p>
                    The AspectJ and AspectWerkz projects have agreed to work together as one team to produce a single aspect-oriented programming platform building on their complementary strengths and expertise.
                    <a href="index-merge.html">Read the announcement published on January 2005</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Notes on AspectWerkz 1.x">
                <p>
                    AspectWerkz 1.x documentation and release notes has been moved <a href="http://aspectwerkz.codehaus.org/aw1/">here</a>.
                    AspectWerkz 1.0 is still actively supported but you are strongly encouraged to migrate to AspectWerkz 2.x.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

