<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
        <author email="alex at gnilux dot com">alexandre vasseur</author>
        <title>General definition issues</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
                <code>AspectWerkz</code> uses a class bytecode manipulation technique for applying aspects to 
                existing Java classes. This means there is no additional language syntax or precompiler necessary.
                It does mean that class bytecode must be intercepted and changed some time before it gets executed.
                Fortunately,
                <code>AspectWerkz</code> provides both offline and online class interception and
                manipulation. Offline manipulation means all class files are scanned and modified in place sometime
                before the application gets executed. Online interception means classes are intercepted as they 
                are loaded by a running application. Both techniques provide costs and benefits. Offline interception
                allows an entire set of classes to be changed once, making runtime execution more efficient, at the
                cost of making the development cycle less efficient (you've have to manipulate a class file every time
                you recompiled the Java source). Online interception makes application execution less efficient 
                (because the class must be modified while the program is running), but eliminates the extra step of 
                changing the class file on every compile.
            </p>
            <p>
                These instructions describe how to create an execution type and a debugger type in
                <code>NetBeans</code>
                to implement online interception for use during the development cycle.
            </p>
            <p>
                Creating the execution and debugger types affects only the project you have open at the time. 
                You must follow these instructions for each separate
                <code>NetBeans</code> project.
            </p>
            <p>
                The instructions have been prepared for
                <code>NetBeans 3.6</code>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Approach">
            <p>
                These instructions demonstrate using the prepared bootclasspath approach to online weaving, by creating a
                new execution type and debugger type. This approach works well with NetBeans.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Initial Setup">
            <subsection name="Install AspectWerkz">
                <p>
                    Install the
                    <code>AspectWerkz</code> distribution, or copy the following jars to an accessible
                    location.
                    <ul>
                        <li>aspectwerkz-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                        <li>aspectwerkz-core-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                        <li>jrexx-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                        <li>trove-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Create an Enhanced Class Loader Jar">
                <p>
                  Using instructions located
                    <a href="online.html#Prepared%20bootclasspath">here</a> to create the
                  enhanced class loader jar. Place the jar in a location accessible by
                    <code>NetBeans</code>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Integrate into Project">
            <p>
                The following instructions must be repeated for each project
                that will use
                <code>AspectWerkz</code>.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Create an Execution Type">
            <ul>
                <li>From the main menu, select Tools/Options</li>
                <li>Right click 'Execution Types', choose 'New', and then choose 'External Execution'. Enter 
                'AspectWerkz Prepared Boot External Execution' or some appropriate name of your choosing. Click the 
                'Finish' button.</li>
                <li>Select the newly created execution type.</li>
                <li>Change the External Process Arguments to the following value:
                    <source><![CDATA[
 -Xbootclasspath/p:/path/to/enhanced/class/loader.jar -Xbootclasspath/a:{bootclasspath}
 {assertEnabled} -cp {filesystems}{:}{classpath} {classname} {arguments}
                     ]]></source>
                 This should all be on one line, with a space between
                    <code>{bootclasspath}</code> and
                    <code>{assertEnable}</code>.
                    <br/>
                 Note that on Windows, you'll need to surround the path to the enhanced class loader jar in double quotes if
                 there are embedded spaces in the path.
                </li>
                <li>Add the following jars to the Boot Classpath:
                    <ul>
                        <li>aspectwerkz-core-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Make any other changes to the execution type to suit your needs.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Create a Debugger Type">
            <ul>
                <li>If the options window is not already open, from the main menu, select Tools/Options</li>
                <li>Right click 'Debugger Types', choose 'New', and then choose 'Default Debugging'. Enter 
                'AspectWerkz Prepared Boot Debubgger' or some appropriate name of your choosing. Click the 
                'Finish' button.</li>
                <li>Select the newly created debugger type.</li>
                <li>Change the External Process Arguments to the following value:
                    <source><![CDATA[
-Xbootclasspath/p:/path/to/enhanced/class/loader.jar -Xbootclasspath/a:{bootclasspath}
 {classic}{assertEnabled}{debuggerOptions} -Djava.compiler=NONE -classpath {q}{filesystems}{q} {main}
                     ]]></source>
                 This should all be on one line, with a space between
                    <code>{bootclasspath}</code> and
                    <code>{classic}</code>.
                    <br/>
                 Note that on Windows, you'll need to surround the path to the enhanced class loader jar in double quotes if
                 there are embedded spaces in the path.
                </li>
                <li>Add the following jars to the Boot Classpath:
                    <ul>
                        <li>aspectwerkz-core-
                            <i>version</i>.jar
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Make any other changes to the execution type to suit your needs.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Activating AspectWerkz in the Project">
            <p>So far, we've only created the customized execution and debugger types. To actually use these in the
               project, the following steps are necessary.
                <subsection name="Select the AspectWerkz Execution Type as the Default">
                    <ul>
                        <li>If the options window is not already open, from the main menu, select Tools/Options</li>
                        <li>Select 'Editing', then select 'Java Sources'.</li>
                        <li>Choose the newly created AspectWerkz execution type as the 'Default Executor'.</li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="Select the AspectWerkz Debugger Type as the Default">
                    <ul>
                        <li>If the options window is not already open, from the main menu, select Tools/Options</li>
                        <li>Select 'Editing', then select 'Java Sources'.</li>
                        <li>Choose the newly created AspectWerkz execution type as the 'Default Debugger'.</li>
                    </ul>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="Mount Necessary Jar Files">
                    <p>
                        Mount the following jar files to the project:
                        <ul>
                            <li>aspectwerkz-
                                <i>version</i>.jar
                            </li>
                            <li>jrexx-
                                <i>version</i>.jar
                            </li>
                            <li>trove-
                                <i>version</i>.jar
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    </p>
                </subsection>
                <subsection name="Configure aspectwerkz.xml">
                    <p>
                        Place the
                        <code>aspectwerkz.xml</code> into a filesystem mounted in the project. When a Java
                        program is run, all filesystems are placed onto the classpath by
                        <code>NetBeans</code>.
                    </p>
                </subsection>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
