<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Papers &amp; Talks</title>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
        <author email="alex at gnilux dot com">alexandre vasseur</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Talks">
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>javaHispano, Nov. 2004, Jonas BonŽr Interview on AOSD</b>
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="http://www.javahispano.org/text.viewer.action?file=jonas_en">Interview in english</a>
                        <br/>
                        <a href="http://www.javahispano.org/text.viewer.action?file=jonas_es">Entrevista en español</a>]
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>JAOO 2004, Annotation-driven AOP for Java (September 2004)</b>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's and Alexandre Vasseur's 45 min session at JAOO 2004.
                        The session goes thru the concept of
                        <i>annotation defined AOP</i> and
                        <i>annotation driven AOP</i>
                        introduced by AspectWerkz.
                        J2SE 5 Tiger annotations brings a new dimension to those concepts. The session demonstrates how strongly typed
                        pointcut are achieved in AspectWerkz (2.0 upcoming codebase) and discuss the advantages and drawbacks of such
                        an approach.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/JAOO2004-AnnotationDrivenAOP.pdf">Session pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>JavaOne 2004, AspectWerkz AOP BOF, AOP in J2EE technical session (June 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        <i>Dynamic Aspect Oriented Programming with AspectWerkz</i>
                        <br/>
                        <i>Aspect Oriented Programming (AOP) in J2EE environments</i>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's and Alexandre Vasseur's 1 hour BOF and 1 hour technical session at JavaOne 2004.
                        The BOF goes thru the HelloWorld AOP tutorial and then delivers some more advanced content around AspectWerkz.
                        The technical session provides concrete demos and code sample about AOP in J2EE, AOP container, annotation driven AOP for
                        caching concerns, JMX monitoring and JAAS security with Spring based configuration of the aspects, under BEA WebLogic Server. It also goes thru the
                        AspectWerkz concept of cross-platform AOP container.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/JavaOne2004-TS1391-J2EEAOP.pdf">Technical session pdf</a>
                        <br/>
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/JavaOne2004-BOF1392-AspectWerkzAOP.pdf">BOF pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>BEA eWorld 2004, Dynamic AOP: SOA for the application (May 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's and Alexandre Vasseur's 1 hour talk providing tech preview of BEA JRockit JVM support for AOP
                        with concrete demos and code samples.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/eWorld2004-1040_boner_aop-soa.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>AOSD 2004, AspectWerkz tutorial (March 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's and Alexandre Vasseur's three hour tutorial providing detailled information about AspectWerkz
                        with emphasis on the
                        <i>Aspects are regular Java classes</i> idea and
                        <i>ease of integration</i>, with a complete
                        demo (available from CVS usually for latest AspectWerkz release, module
                        <i>tutorial-aosd2004</i>).
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/aosd2004_tutorial_aspectwerkz.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>AOSD 2004, Invited Industry Talk (March 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        <i>What are the key issues for commercial AOP use - how does AspectWerkz address them?</i>
                        <br/>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's keynote about commercial AOP use and design decision for AspectWerkz.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/InvitedTalkAOSD2004.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>BeJUG JavaPolis, Antwerp 2003 (December 16, 2003)</b>
                        <br/>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's one hour talk provides an introduction to AspectWerkz (targets 0.9) and gives concrete
                        hands on samples (Unit Of Work pattern, JAAS security for POJOs).
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/bejug-aspectwerkz-boner.ppt.gz">ppt</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Papers">
            <p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <b>TheServerSide.com, AspectWerkz 2: An Extensible Aspect Container (Nov. 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        In this article, Jonas Bon&#233;r introduces the new AspectWerkz 2.x architecture.
                        <br/>
                        AspectWerkz 2.x has been designed to be an extensible AOP container where any kind of
                        aspects can coexist ranging from Spring aspects to AspectJ aspects.
                        <br/>
                        The article explains
                        why this architecture is beneficial to the Java AOP communtity and explains the benefits
                        and drawbacks of running AOP Alliance, Spring and AspectJ aspects within the AspectWerkz
                        Extensible Aspect Container. It concludes with performance figures.
                        <br/>
                        [<a href="http://www.theserverside.com/articles/article.tss?l=AspectWerkzP1">Read more</a>] 
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <b>BEA dev2dev, Enabling Aspect-Oriented Programming in WebLogic Server using the JRockit Management API (June 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        In this article, you will learn the basic AOP concepts as well as how to apply AOP to your J2EE applications using AspectWerkz, a dynamic AOP framework. The hands-on tutorial explains how to use AOP to track EJB CMP's container generated JDBC queries.
                        <br/>
                        You will learn how to integrate AOP in your BEA environment, using a standard offline class post-processing mechanism, class-load time integration in BEA WebLogic Server 8.1 and a dedicated BEA JRockit Management API module that delivers best performance with a minimal integration effort.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="http://dev2dev.bea.com/technologies/soa/businesslogic/articles/boner_vasseur.jsp">Read more</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>AOSD 2004, Dynamic AOP WorkShop (March 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        <i>Dynamic AOP and Runtime Weaving for Java - How does AspectWerkz Address it?</i>
                        <br/>
                        Alexandre Vasseur's technical paper about dynamic AOP and especially the feature allowing
                        addition of new pointcuts at runtime using HotSwap (since 1.0-beta1).
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/aosd2004-daw-aspectwerkz.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>AOSD 2004, Invited Industry Talk Abstract Paper (March 2004)</b>
                        <br/>
                        <i>What are the key issues for commercial AOP use - how does AspectWerkz address them?</i>
                        <br/>
                        The abstract paper of Jonas Bon&#233;r's invited talk at AOSD 2004, gives an in depth discussion
                        about the key issues for commercial AOP use and how AspectWerkz tries to address them.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="htt://codehaus.org/~jboner/papers/aosd2004_commercial_aop_aspectwerkz.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>AOSD 2004, (technical paper) (October 2003)</b>
                        <br/>
                        <i>AspectWerkz - dynamic AOP for Java</i>
                        <br/>
                        Jonas Bon&#233;r's technical paper about the architecture, design and implementation AspectWerkz.
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="htt://codehaus.org/~jboner/papers/aosd2004_aspectwerkz.pdf">pdf</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                    <li>
                        <b>Hooking architecture (since 0.8) (August 12, 2003)</b>
                        <br/>
                        The hooking architecture allows class load time weaving for all Java version since 1.3 and all
                        JVMs (Sun, IBM, BEA).
                        <br/>
                        [
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/AspectWerkz-online-architecture.pdf.zip">pdf</a>,
                        <a href="/downloads/papers/AspectWerkz-online-architecture.ppt.zip">ppt</a>]
                    </li>
                    <br/>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>