<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Testimonials</title>
        <author email="jboner at codehaus dot org">jonas bon&#233;r</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Testimonials">
            <subsection name="Multimedia Caf&#233;: commercial usage">
                <p>
                    "Multimedia Caf&#233; (www.mmcafe.com.br) is a web development company
                    located in S„o Paulo, Brazil. Multimedia Caf&#233; started in 1996,
                    and since its inception, it's been doing
                    <!--                    innovative and award-winning -->
                    projects for companies such as Citibank, Parmalat,
                    HP, Motorola and Toyota. In the new version of its
                    <!--                    widely recognized -->
                    content management product, mmPublish, Multimedia Caf&#233;
                    and Bluebox Technologies (www.bluebox.com.br) partnered to create
                    <!--                    a jaw-dropping --> a new
                    Portal Management System, and AspectWerkz is being
                    used everywhere: from the plug-in architecture to security,
                    caching, persistence, content management, indexing, aggregation,
                    syndication and segregation, with outstanding success, even within
                    a very tight schedule."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Our mission was to deliver a completely outstanding and
                    revolutionary architecture, packed with cool features, to
                    Multimedia Caf&#233;. When we found AspectWerkz, we thought:
                    'that's it!', and started working right away. After reading the
                    documentation and playing with it for a while, we had a prototype
                    for mmPublish 3's core services running in just a few days.
                    Thanks to AspectWerkz's practical approach, Aspect-Orientation
                    was made so easy and straight-forward that we could teach it to
                    beginner programmers in a couple of hours, and got an impressive
                    productivity boost."
                </p>
                <p>
                    - Carlos Villela, lead architect for the 3.0 version of
                    mmPublish, Bluebox Technologies
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="AspectWerkz: aspects done right">
                <p>
                    "I believe a new evolutionary step in the history of
                    Aspect-Oriented Programming has been reached with AspectWerkz,
                    from Jonas Bon&#233;r. When I read the documentation for the first
                    time, I was already struck how simple and straightforward
                    everything is with AspectWerkz. Don't be mistaken:
                    the software covers all the known features of AOP as it is
                    defined today (advice, pointcuts, introductions, runtime modes,
                    etc...) but what is striking is how everything fits nicely
                    together with a simple XML definition file."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Keep an eye on AspectWerkz, I believe it will soon become a
                    major player in the AOP world."
                </p>
                <p>
                    -
                    <a href="http://www.freeroller.net/page/cbeust/20030409#aspectwerks_aspects_done_right">C&#233;dric Beust</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="And The Winner of the AOP Wars is..">
                <p>
                    So drum roll please, the winner in the AOP wars is none other than...AspectWerkz!
                </p>
                <p>
                    Uncanny mastery of the subject matter, comprehensive functionality,
                    impressive performance and most of all excellent documentation.
                    For all other AOP pretenders please pay your respects to the master, Jonas Bonér!
                </p>
                <p>
                    -
                    <a href="http://www.freeroller.net/page/ceperez/20030620#and_the_winner_of_the">Carlos E. Perez</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Aspects are now usable">
                <p>
                    "A new software package Aspectwerkz looks like it might really
                    bring Aspects to Java for good (if Xerox doesn't mind)."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Well, I definitely was skeptical at first, but after reading
                    <a href="http://www.freeroller.net/page/cbeust/20030409#aspectwerks_aspects_done_right">C&#233;dric's</a>
                    post on this I have to say I am very impressed.
                    Aspects seemed like they would confuse more developers than
                    help given the complicated implementations that I have seen.
                    This package though is amazing and leverages all the software
                    the open source community has to give."
                </p>
                <p>
                    -
                    <a href="http://homepage.mac.com/spullara/rants/C1464297901/E1986247138/index.html">Sam Pullara</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="AspectWerkz is impressive">
                <p>
                    "AspectWerks is the new kid on the java AOP block. The brain
                    child of the obviously talented Jonas Bon&#233;r, I've been
                    completely blown away by both it's power and simplicity."
                </p>
                <p>
                    "Go on, check it out, I know you want to :)"
                </p>
                <p>
                    -
                    <a href="http://www.rocketred.com.au/blogs/kevin/archives/2003_04_07.html#000157">Kevin O'Neill</a>
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

